A Guide to the John F. Riordan papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA191
Rockefeller Archive Center
John F. Riordan papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1934-1983, bulk 1968-1982
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Riordan, John, 1903-
FA191
2.64 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
John F. Riordan, 1903-1988. Mathematician and engineer.
Born in Ansonia, Connecticut, Riordan was orphaned when he was six years old. He went on to become his high school's valedictorian and attended Yale University. After graduating in 1923 with a B.S., Riordan worked for the United Electric Light and Power Company (now Consolidated Edison Company) and American Telephone and Telegraph Company until 1934. He then joined the staff of Bell Telephone Laboratories in New York where he revived the branch of mathematics known as combinatorial theory. For a number of years Riordan concentrated on studies of the distribution of currents in railway networks and tracks and in the ground, and the effects of these currents on telephone circuits. His other mathematical interests included Boolean algebra in switching, number theory in cable splicing, and probability studies of telephone traffic. Riordan also served as a consultant to various government agencies, including the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Because of his blindness in one eye caused by a detached retina when he was seven years old, Riordan was unable to serve in World War II but worked as a consultant instead for the Atomic Energy Commission.
After his retirement from Bell Laboratories in 1968, Riordan was appointed an affiliate of The Rockefeller University, where he worked with Mark Kac. In 1979, he received the appointment of adjunct faculty member, a post he held until 1985.
In 1929, Riordan published a collection of his own short stories, "On the Make." He was also a critic for the Saturday Review and edited The Salient, the literary magazine for the New School of Social Research. In 1958, he published "An Introduction to Combinatorial Analysis, "which was translated into Russian in 1962 and considered to be a definitive work in the field. Riordan published "Scholastic Service Systems" in 1962 and "Combinatorial Identities" in 1968. He also authored over 60 articles in professional journals.
He died of Alzheimer's disease on August 27, 1988. Riordan had been married to the late Mavis McIntosh; had two daughters, Sheila Riordan of Scituate, MA, and Kathleen T. Speeth of El Cerrito, CA; six grandchildren; and four great-grandchildren.
Notes: Riordan was a member of the following: American Association for the Advancement of Science, American Mathematical Society, Institute of Mathematical Statistics, and the Mathematical Association of America.
On his 75th birthday, the Journal of Combinatorial Theory dedicated a "Festschrift," or commemorative composition, in his honor.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological and alphabetical order.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 R479
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Statistics; Mathematical statistics; Mathematics; Probabilities; Algebra; Combinatorial analysis; Medical research; Medical education; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Riordan, John, 1903-
- Correspondence, 1967-1982; 1; 1 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes abstracts of papers, notes, papers, and reference letters.
  Correspondents include George E. Andrews, Richard Askey, Edward A. Bender, Leonard Carlitz, C.Y. Chao, L. Comtet, Leroy J. Dickey, Robert Donaghey, D. Dumont, R.C. Entringer, John A. Ewell, Harley Flanders, D. Foata, H.O. Foulkes, Robert Gilmer, Karl Goldberg, Jay Goldman, H.W. Gould, Richard K. Guy, Deborah and Franklin Tepper Haimo, Paul Halmos, Peter L. Hammer, Frank Harary, Verner E. Hoggatt, Jr., Joseph B. Kadane, Gill Kalai, Irving Kaplansky, Murray S. Klamkin, David A. Klarner, Donald E. Knuth, John Konvalina, G. Kreweras, Robert E. Krieger, Shri H.V. Krishna, W. Kuich, Aert H. Kuipers, Jean L. Lavoie, Joshua Lederberg, D. Lehmer, Colin L. Mallows, Albert W. Marshall, Valeric Mike, New York Academy of Sciences, Princeton University Press, D. Rogers, David Roselle, William J. Rosenberg, Gian-Carlo Rota, Bruce Rothschild, Joseph Rotman, Morris Schreiber, M.P. Schutzenberger, Frederick Seitz, Neil J.A. Sloane, Paul R. Stein, Lajos Takacs, Stephen Tanny, Stephen Thaler, L. Toscano, W.T. Tutte, Glenn Whitehead, Wiley-Interscience.
  Subjects include reviews of papers by Riordan.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical order by name of correspondent, then in chronological order.
  - A-I
    - A, 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C, 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D, 1969-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - E, 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - F, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - G, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - H, 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - I, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - J-Sl
    - J, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - K-Ko, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Kr-Kz, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - L, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - M, 1968-1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - N, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - O, 1969-1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - P-Q, 1969-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - R-Ros, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Rot-Rz, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - S-Sl, 1968-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sp-Z
    - Sp-Sz, 1968-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - T-V, 1968-1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - W, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Y-Z, 1969-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Partial/Unidentified, 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Manuscripts, 1941-1973, undated; 2; 0.2 Cubic Feet
  Includes correspondence, galleys, notes, and referee reports.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
  - "The Asymptotic Distribution of Labeled Trees...", undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Cable Splicing for Crosstalk Purposes", 1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "A Character in Search of a Symbol", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Distribution of Acyclic Functions by Number of Ones", undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "The Distribution of Crossing of Chords...", 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "The Enumeration of Permutations...", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Galley Proofs, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Historical Capsule of Queuing Theory", undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "How to Get Something for Free", undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "The Joint Distribution of Permutations...", undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "The Many Faces of Ballotry", Ch. 1, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Mappings of Acyclic and Parking Functions" (w/D. Foata), 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Moments of the Distribution of Inversions in Labeled Trees", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Mrs. Mannerings Recessional", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "A Brief Note on Catalan Parentheses", undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Probability Theory", 1941-1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Review of Percy Alexander MacMahon, Collected Papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Memorabilia, 1962-1983; 3; 1 folder
  Includes an article ("The Math Makers" re Bell Labs. In Telephone Review, May 1962, pp. 16-19 - includes only a photograph of Riordan), bibliographies of others, and programs to special events.
  No arrangement.
  - Memorabilia, 1962-1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Notebooks, undated; 4; 0.8 Cubic Feet
  Includes correspondence and notes.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Analysis of Combinations (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bell Bernoulk and Other Numbers (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Circuit Theory (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Classification of Permutations (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Electromagnetic Theory - Math Notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Permutations (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Probability and Statistics, I (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Probability and Statistics, II (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Probability Theory (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Telephone Trunking (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Trees - S.P. Labeled Networks (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Notes, 1934-1973; 5; 1 folder
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Includes articles, correspondence, and miscellaneous mathematical notes.
  - Notes, 1934-1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Photographs, undated; 6; 1 folder
  Includes group shots and postcards.
  - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Reprint Requests, undated; 7; 1 folder
  Includes cards and forms for requesting copies of Riordan's reprints.
  - Reprint Requests (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Reprints, 1951-1980; 8; 0.2 Cubic Feet
  Not complete set.
  Includes bibliography and list of collaborators on papers.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Reprints, 1951-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Reprints, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Reprints, 1971-1980 (Box 6, Folder 3)